Gothic II: The History of Khorinis!
Hello again! Arkadiusz 'Arkadikuss' Woźniak here.
Do you still remember our previous movie,
in which we mentioned about mysterious and UNRELEASED addon to the first Gothic?
We created a material, in which we will tell you more about this addon at your requests.
Some of you might ask - what does that have to do with our project?
It would seem that it is a seperate topic, right?
Not exactly.
In the 'History of Khorinis' we will use some IDEAS abandoned by the Piranha Bytes,
which were created for the purposes of that addon, for instance the Demon Hunters.
Of course in GOOD taste.
Your concern was an another issue.
We received many requests for information about Gothic Sequel,
so we couldn't fail you.
The team of the 'History of Khorinis' decided to respond to faithful fans of Gothic
and show you the most important information about that mysterious addon.
Are you ready? Make yourself comfortable and listen!
The Addon
Let's start from the beginning: from the first public information about the addon.
They appeared on the german forum World of Gothic in 2001 - just after the release of the first game.
Piranha Bytes' staff asked the players what - in their opinion - should be in the addon, on which they had worked.
There were many suggestions, however Phenomedia AG - co-owner of the Piranha Bytes -
signed an agreement with JoWood for global distribution of games.
As a result of the new owner's suggestion, they made a decision that it will be better to start with a new game, rather than with the addon.
Piranha Bytes started a work on Gothic 2, and the addon to the first Gothic was cancelled.
As a result, the topic of addon has subsided for years.
Until now!
The leak.
The silence has continued for almost sixteen years and it would seem that this topic became completely forgotten.
Many players, who started to play Gothic later than the day of the release
had not an idea that any addon had been ever planned.
However, the turning point of that topic was a leak of new information on the russian forum World of Players in September 2016.
The owner of the portal - MaGoth - published the screenshots and several information, claiming that they came from that unreleased addon to Gothic.
Furthermore, he also claimed that he has got that addon!
Many people thoug ht that it is fake, but precise analysis of those screenshots allow to confirm their authenticity.
Before we go to the same analysis, we want to remind
that MaGoth deleted the thread about the unreleased addon of Gothic 1 and stopped giving information to anyone at the request of former member of the Piranha Bytes'.
On the screenshots we can see new armors:
The Royal Guard (actually an earlier version of the Paladins),
or the Demon Hunters.
Those armors can be found also in the official artbook released by Piranha called 'The Art of Gothic 3'.
ATTENTION! In this place we want to inform and highlight one thing - that book
HAS NOTHING in common with the artbook added to the polish and german collectors edition of Gothic 3.
The book 'The Art of Gothic' was sold separately for a while - and it includes also tens of pages about first two games of Gothic Saga.
Besides, we can also find artworks from the Gothic 3
which most of them cannot be found in the artbook from the collectors edition.
Our team bought that book many years ago. Currently it can be found only on foreign online auctions.
Let's go back to its content.
Some of the monsters which appeared on the screenshots of the addon can be found in that book as well - including skeleton wolf and mutated lizard.
The models of those armors and animals were NEVER published anywhere, which clearly indecates their authenticity.
The last important information is fact that the authenticity of files was confirmed by our lead coder Avallach,
who analyzed the archives with GothicVDFS - a tool written by NicoDE, former member of the Piranha Bytes.
The Plot.
The addon had a working title 'Gothic Sequel'
and its history began at a time of the end of the Gothic 1 - right AFTER the banishment of Sleeper.
Similar to Gothic 2, Xardas had succesfully escaped from the temple before its collapse,
and by using magic, he brought the Nameless Hero back to his tower, which is not placed in the Khorinis.
It's still about the same old tower situated in the Mine Valley!
Our hero after the rescue by the Necromancer, make a short conversation with him, from which he learn that entire Mine Valley is full of Orcs.
As it turns out later, the biggest threat is... Sleeper, who may be able to return to realm of humans with the army of demons.
It's because of the destruction of the Magic Barrier, which has weakened a structure dividing the dimensions.
Hence the demons are able to enter freely into our world from another spacetimes.
Let's make a short break and remind the words of Hyglas - the Firge Mage from the Monastery in Khorinis.
Here's what we can heard from him in Gothic 2:
'Found anything out yet?
I'm not sure, but it seems that current
constellation of stars foreshadow the problem.
What problems?
The matter dividing two worlds become very thin.
If somebody had wanted to open the passage, he would do this by using only a small part of the power required to do this under different circumstances.
The demons can use those passages, to infiltrate into our world.'
Sounds very familiar, isn't it?
That fragment is just a remnant of the Gothic Sequel!
Let's back to the plot of the addon.
Xardas warns the Nameless Hero, that entire Mine Valley might become the one biggest portal leading to the demon's dimension!
So the fate of the Hero is prejudged - he has to stop Sleeper's armies at all costs.
Unfortunately, our hero is very weak,
so similar to Gothic 2 he needs to recover his lost strenght.
Xardas sends the Nameless Hero to the Old Camp.
Meantime Xardas is trying to find out more about the demon's that they appear from nowhere (and murder everyone).
The Magician gives also a letter to a certain important person, then he teleports him to the Old Camp,
or rather its remnants.
It turns out that the person to which the message is addressed is none other than our old friend Diego!
Currently he is the leader of the Refugees Camp, which was founded at the place of the Old Camp.
From Diego our hero learns that King Rhobar II arrived with army to the Mine Valley and he resides in the mountain fortress.
AT THIS POINT WE REMIND THAT AT THE STAGE OF THE FIRST GOTHIC AND THAT ADDON
THE PIRANHA ASSUMED KHORINIS AS A PART OF THE MAINLAND.
We got a confirmation about this fact from the reliable source.
In the addon we learn that Rhobar came with his army from beyond the mountains.
The ruler comes from the capital not only in order to save the mines and extraction of the magic ore.
There are rumours that he is looking for something within the Colony.
Diego also reveals the reason why he didn't leave the valley - it is more real vision of the lost war with the Orcs.
Regarding the people of the Colony we learn that many convicts have been killed,
many of them escaped, but - surprisingly
a huge groups of refugees came to the Valley from all over the country,
who (like Diego and part of the convicts) seek a shelter from the war.
Diego gives the sword to the Nameless Hero and sends him to help the people in the Outer Rim,
so that our hero could earn a little money and partially restore his skills.
Bezimienny is also allocated to the baron's old chamber, in which he can sleep.
Diego informs the Hero, that the Collapse of the Barrier destroyed all runes and magical artifacts.
An harbringer of this event we can find in the first Gothic - in the dialogue with Saturas about destroying the Barrier:
'The explosion will be merely of a magical nature, it will only destroy
everything that's been modified by the magic inside the Barrier.
There is no danger to us human beings.'
It is interesting that the idea of destroying magic runes was used in Gothic 3.
Apparently, Lester has been busy during his stay in the Mountain Fortress.
During the study of an ancient magical books, he found a way to create a new runes
and he can pass this knowledge to the Nameless Hereo, and also learn him the magical arcanas.
It is worth mentioning that the concept of creating runes (and the rune tables) have JUST appeared in Gothic 2.
However, Piranha Bytes didn't TRY to explain the reason why we couldn't create the runes in the first Gothic.
Lester also mentions that our buddy - Milten
- is in the Mountain Fortress, and he informs our hero about mysterious figures
in black robes. He also tells us about the plague that spreads throughout the commercial disctrict of the Camp.
Infected people are slowly turning into the zombies.
Those figures, which were mentioned by Lester are the dementors - later as known as the Seekers from Gothic 2.
Locations and details
The devastation of the Old Camp.
In the Old Camp many things has changed, we can see a collapsed roof above the marketplace
and serious gaps in the walls of the Outer Rim. At the place of those gaps, we can see a provisional barricades.
Some houses have been also destroyed, and near the scene on which In Extremo played there are a lot of boulders.
But the most important thing is the damaged castle tower.
What is so interesting in that tower?
Let's remind a fragment of the intro from Gothic 2.
As you can see in the intro, a thunder hits in the tower and destroys THE SAME
piece placed exactly in the same place, which we can see in the addon.
That damage does not appear in Gothic 2!
It's just an another remnant of the addon, used in the Gothic 2.
The collapse of the Barrier and thunderstorms
- and as a consequence the fires - were the reason of the huge devastation in the Camp.
And they are responsible for a truly 'lunar landscape' which we are watching.
By the way - as you remember in Gothic 2 the Old Camp have been also destroyed.
This time Piranha Bytes went forward and made that the whole of the Outer Rim have been disappeared off the face of the earth,
and in its place we can see only ashes.
It is a living proof how many ideas from the addon to Gothic were used or developed in one way or another in the next game.
THE INTRO OF THE ADDON
As regards the intro we have a shocking information for you!
Well, the entire intro of Gothic 2 (except the title logo) has been created for the purposes of the addon to Gothic 1!
NicoDe mentioned about this on the forum World of Gothic in 2012,
confirming using the fragments from the addon in Gothic 2.
Another, confirmatory proof is a scene from the intro, in which the Nameless Hero is summoned to the tower.
The tower is empty and it is not its interior from Gothic 2!
Comparing it to the interior from Gothic Sequel we can recognise immediately that it is the same place!
The case with the heroes clothing is similar to the previous one.
He's got a new outfit with suspenders - in both the intro and the addon to Gothic 1.
Besides the scenes, which we know there was a leak of new scenes of that intro.
We can confirm their authencity with the 'Art of Gothic'.
The entire intro of the addon is found in the concept visualization with the detailed descriptions.
From the beginning we can see Diego and Gorn looking on the collapse of the Barrier,
the scene of thunderstorms and lightings hitting throghout the camp - of which the biggest lighting hits in the castle tower.
Next scene is a partial destruction of the tower, and the next one is a view on flaming circle
and a lot of smoke around the Old Camp.
In the next scenes we can see one of the Orcs, who at first checks the burned area,
and then he gives the signal to escape from prison.
From the description of pictures we learn that after leaving beyond the Colony,
the Orcs attack the first encountered village, murdering everyone who get in the way of them.
In the sequel the animators has limited that scene to capture the charge
and fight with soldiers-bowmen, similar to them from the intro of Gothic 1.
Another scene are the same - in both the intro of Sequel and the intro of Gothic 2.
We can see how Xardas teleports the Nameless Hero from the Temple to his tower.
Tora the Warrior.
On the screenshots we can see a rather unusal for the Gothic figure - a woman-warrior.
On one of them we can see event a fragment of dialouue between her and the Nameless Hero.
After the translation from german we learn that she asks hero who he is and why he apparead in this place so suddenly.
We meet with her at the begging of the game - just after the teleportation from the Xardas' tower.
We know that her name is TORA and she handles a quaterstaff.
She was one of the leading and the most important character in the project.
We also learn that she is the King's scout.
Piranhas planned a transfer of her concept to the plot of Gothic 2 in the form of the woman-paladin.
It happened at the stage of the development of the Paladin Order with the chivalry look.
However, the idea was abandoned, because the concept of emancipation of women didn't fit to the final vision of Gothic 2.
The only remnant is this artwork and her 3D model during sex scene,
which was later used by the Piranha's in the Red Lantern (to the scene with Nadia).
Hagen
In the addon Hagen also appears - he is seen on the screenshot next to King Rhobar
and he wears the heavy paladin armor,
because that name can be found in the script of the addon.
even if looks similar to the Royal Guard armor from Gothic 1.
We will tell you about the Guard in a moment.
Rhobar's daughter
As you remember from Gothic, King Rhobar had a wife.
She had been murdered by the part of conspiring nobles many years before the action of Gothic 1
in order to get rid of General Lee.
'There was a time when I led a very different life. I was one of the best generals of this country.
I've spent my whole life fighting for my country.
But the nobles didn't like me, because the King listened to my advice.
And they knew I posed a threat to their dirty business.
I hadn't counted on their insidiousness.
They used the King's wife to get me.
I was blamed for her pointless murder. King Rhobar had no other choice.'
As it turns out, the king and the queen have a daughter, who was taken by Rhobar to the Valley.
She even wears a diadem.
More interesting is fact that Piranha planned much hotter story with the princess, which proof can be seen on the screenshot.
Translating them from the top, we can read:
1. Undress yourself and lie down.
2. Bathe yourself!
3. You are finished, bitch!
As you can see, a comment is needless.
The Royal Guard - an early version of the Paladins.
The Royal Guard is an elite part of the Myrthana's army.
We met them in Gothic - in the intro of the game we can see its soldiers who bring the Nameless Hero on the verge of precicipe.
Besides, the royal guard armors can be found in the files of the game and we can summon them without problems by using codes.
In the sequel they were called the Paladins - they have decided to change the Paladins armors into typical chivalrous armors
during the development of dragons in the early stage of Gothic 2.
From the addon's point of view, there were an elite troops, with their own equipment and representing a high battle value.
We could not say about the high battle value in Myrthana's regular infantry,
not to even mention militia and peasants, who were rather a cannon fodder.
The Demon Hunters
We told about them in the previous movie.
As you remember, the files of their textures remained in the final version of Gothic 2.
It is worth mentioning that the Demon Hunters appeared in another game
from the Piranha Bytes - in Risen 3 as an unused idea 'in action'.
In Gothic Sequel we meet also the guild called the Healers, with the look similar to the Spanish Inqusition.
They help sick people and fight with the plague, which attacked people.
Fights on the arena.
As you remember from Gothic 1, in the Old Camp there was the arena,
on which we had a chance to fight with one of two enemies.
In the addon, the authors wanted to expanded this theme.
From the published fragment of the document we can learn
that the player not only receives a money for winning fights in the arena,
but also he increases his reputation by gaining new titles and prestige points.
The player could also find a new enemies myself, but not all the enemies would accept his challenge to duel.
If the player had not meet with the requirements assigned to different warriors, they would not accept his challenge.
Optionally, in the game was planned a possibility that the player was challenged to the duels by the low-level warriors.
Moreover, the document mentions about the character - the master of the arena,
who had a role to give information to players about their career, successess and failures in the arena.
A won fights were awarded with gold, and society of the camp was
supposed to gather around the arena in every evening, in order to watch the fights.
The demon's plague
Besides the monsters coming from other dimensions, all animals living throughout Colony are also turned into demons!
Besieds the demon lizard and skeleton wolf ALL monster from the addon can be found in Gothic 2 and the Night of the Raven!
The demons were previously:
Black troll
Demon snapper
Skeleton goblin
and also Skeleton shadowbeast
In the Night of the Raven we can also see Demon Scavenger - turned into prairie species.
Known NPC's
On one of the many screenshots we can see a sick NPC named Bartok.
A character, who is known in Gothic 2 as a hunter.
Is is the same act just like with Canthar, who appared in the demo of the first Gothic.
However, he didn't appear in the final version of the game, but he was used in Gothic 2 as a merchant.
We also met another two names known from Gothic 2 - Ruga
and Agon.
Then in scritps of the addon we can find more characters known from Gothic 2 - it is worth listing Hyglas
(his dialogue about from Gothic 2 was qutoed by us), or Brutus.
Deleted Animations
An another interesting information is fact that Piranha tried to make fully animated models of open hands to replace the model of 'fists'.
We can be seen both on graphics in the 'Art of Gothic' and in the gameplay of the addon.
Because of technical problems that idea was abandoned and in Gothic 2 we still see the fists known from the first game.
We know also that Piranha developed an animation of the 'movement' of women's hair - it can be seen on the screenshot with Tora in the arena of the Refugees Camp.
New skills
On the screenshot, which shows the statistics menu, we can see skills like:
create runes
forge weapons
and alchemy, so the skills, which appeared later in Gothic 2.
However, there are some new skills like:
cooking
a new fighting skill - besides one-hand weapons, two-hand weapons, crossbows and bows - was quaterstaff fighting,
which was confirmed by the fact that Tora was fighting with this kind of weapon.
In statistics menu you can also notice a skill called 'fletcher'.
Hence, we have had an opportunity to making the arrows and bows.
The last skill, which was not available for our hero, was armourer.
The cancellation of the addon
As we mentioned in the beginning of our video, an abandonment of the project was connected with pressure from the mother-company - Phenomedia
and confusion around the new publisher - JoWood.
Phenomedia didn't want to disappoint the company that came to help.
Those events coincided with the Mike's Hoge and Björn's Pankratz decision about abandoning the plans of working on a new shooter
in Deus EX style - both guys wanted to take care of something that they have known, so they went back to Gothic.
More details about this we can find in the second part of the movie 'Gothic in a nutshell'.
In the beginning Gothic 2 was to remain in the climate from the first Gothic.
However, during the development of the game and implementantion of the Dragons and the Paladin Order
in chivalry version, the shape of the game has changed into this, what we can see nowadays.
What next with the unreleased addon?
However, the future of the unreleased addon is very uncertain.
A thread on the russian forum has been deleted on the behalf of former member of the Piranha Bytes,
and the administrator, who was responsible for publication of all information, still remains silent.
He doesn't want to publish antyhing about the addon - especially the files of the
addon, which it would be a step against the Piranha Bytes' will.
Of course, it is possible to consider complete the addon - even as a modification.
Unfortunately - without the source files, it is in theory a possible task, but in practice very difficult to implementation.
And that's all about the unreleased addon.
We are waiting for your opinion and comments. And of course, we encourage you to subscribe - we are preparing another materials!
Farewell and... for Gomez!
Idea and realization – Mariusz 'Bgb' Pawlak and Piotr ‘Dark’ Czołnkowski
Editing - Mateusz 'Pawłoch' Pawłowski
Music - Cezary 'Fang' Wnuk
Narrator: Arkadiusz 'Arkadikuss' Woźniak
With thanks to - Marek 'Mark56' Karas, Szymon 'Szmyk' Żak and Jan 'Johnny' Baryła
English subtitles: Bartosz ‘Kereth’ Biały based on polish subitles made by Szymon ‘Szmyk’ Żak